Parsing is the crucial compiler phase that determines if a sequence of tokens conforms to a language's grammar. While
top-down parsers predict the structure from the start symbol, bottom-up parsers build the parse tree from the input
tokens, gradually reducing substrings to non-terminals until the start symbol is reached. This process essentially
reverses a rightmost derivation.
Context-Free Grammars provide the rules our parser will follow. In bottom-up parsing, the core operation is finding a
'handle' – a specific substring in our current form that matches a production rule's right-hand side and can be
correctly reduced to its left-hand side non-terminal. This handle represents a pivotal point for reduction, ensuring we
reverse the rightmost derivation correctly. We often augment the grammar with a new start symbol to simplify parsing
completion.
Shift-reduce parsing is the most common bottom-up technique. It employs two main components: a parsing stack, which
accumulates processed symbols and states, and an input buffer, holding the remaining tokens. The parser operates in a
loop, performing one of four actions: 'Shift', where it moves the next input token to the stack; 'Reduce', where it
identifies a handle on top of the stack and replaces it with the corresponding non-terminal; 'Accept', indicating
successful parsing; or 'Error', if no valid action is found.
Let's trace a simple arithmetic expression, 'id + id * id', through a shift-reduce parser. We begin with an empty stack
and the full input. The parser will strategically 'shift' tokens onto the stack until a 'handle' is formed. Once a
handle is recognized, a 'reduce' action replaces that sequence of symbols on the stack with its corresponding
non-terminal. This cycle of shifting and reducing continues, gradually transforming the input tokens into higher-level
grammatical constructs, until only the start symbol remains on the stack and the input is exhausted.
While simple shift-reduce is intuitive, it often encounters ambiguities, such as whether to 'shift' the next token or
'reduce' the symbols on the stack. These 'shift-reduce' or 'reduce-reduce' conflicts require a more sophisticated
approach. This is where LR parsers come in. LR parsers are a family of powerful bottom-up parsers that use a fixed
number of 'lookahead' symbols from the input to deterministically make parsing decisions, scanning left-to-right to
produce a rightmost derivation in reverse.
LR parsers are driven by a 'parsing table,' a crucial component built during compiler design. This table is constructed
by analyzing the grammar to create a 'DFA of viable prefixes,' a finite automaton whose states are collections of 'LR
items'. An LR item, like 'A → α.β', indicates how much of a production we've seen so far. Operations like 'Closure' and
'GOTO' systematically expand these item sets and define transitions between states, ultimately populating the 'Action'
and 'GOTO' tables that guide the parser's decisions at runtime.
The LR family includes several types, each offering a trade-off between parsing power and table size. LR(0) is the
simplest, without lookahead for reductions. SLR(1) improves upon this by using FOLLOW sets to guide reduce decisions.
Canonical LR(1) is the most powerful, resolving the most conflicts by maintaining detailed lookahead information, but
creates large tables. LALR(1) strikes a practical balance, merging LR(1) states with identical 'cores' to produce
smaller tables while retaining significant power, making it a popular choice for tools like YACC and Bison.
In summary, bottom-up parsing is a fundamental technique in compiler construction, building syntactic structure from
the ground up by reducing tokens to higher-level grammar symbols. Shift-reduce parsing, particularly with the
deterministic power of LR parsers, offers efficiency and robust error detection. This powerful approach is not just
academic; it underpins how modern compilers process your code, how domain-specific languages are understood, and how
syntax checkers ensure the correctness of your programs.