Imagine a bustling city intersection where two cars approach from opposite directions, both needing to turn left. Each
car is waiting for the other to move, but neither can proceed because they are mutually blocking each other. This
endless wait, a complete standstill, is analogous to an OS Deadlock, where processes get stuck waiting for resources
held by others.
For a deadlock to grip an operating system, four specific conditions must all be present simultaneously. These are:
Mutual Exclusion, meaning resources cannot be shared; Hold and Wait, where a process holds resources while waiting for
more; No Preemption, implying resources cannot be forcibly taken; and finally, Circular Wait, forming a closed loop of
dependencies.
Consider two processes, P1 and P2, needing exclusive access to Printer A (R1) and Scanner B (R2). P1 first acquires
Printer A, demonstrating mutual exclusion. Now P1 needs Scanner B, but P2 has already acquired it. P1 now exemplifies
'hold and wait': holding Printer A while waiting for Scanner B, which is currently unavailable.
In our scenario, Scanner B cannot be forcibly taken from P2 to give to P1; P2 must voluntarily release it – this is 'No
Preemption'. With P1 holding Printer A and waiting for Scanner B, and P2 holding Scanner B and waiting for Printer A, we
see a 'Circular Wait'. Each process in the chain is waiting for a resource held by the next, creating an unbreakable
dependency loop.
To formally detect deadlock, we use Resource-Allocation Graphs. Processes are circles, resources are squares. An arrow
from a process to a resource means a request; an arrow from a resource to a process means it's assigned. When a cycle
forms in this graph, like P1 requesting R2 which P2 holds, and P2 requesting R1 which P1 holds, it signals a deadlock.
Operating systems employ various strategies to manage deadlocks. We can try to prevent them by negating one of the four
conditions, or use avoidance algorithms to ensure we never enter an unsafe state. If deadlocks are allowed, we need
detection mechanisms to find them, followed by recovery procedures to break them. Each approach has its own complexities
and performance implications.
Deadlock Prevention proactively blocks one of the four conditions, perhaps by enforcing resource preemption or by
requiring processes to request all resources at once. Deadlock Avoidance, on the other hand, dynamically decides whether
to grant a resource request. It uses information about future resource needs to ensure that granting a request will not
lead the system into an unsafe state, like the Banker's Algorithm does.
When deadlocks are allowed to occur, the system relies on detection algorithms, often periodically analyzing
resource-allocation graphs, to identify them. Once a deadlock is confirmed, recovery measures are initiated. These might
involve terminating one or more deadlocked processes, or preempting resources from a process to break the circular wait.
Both detection and recovery come with significant performance overhead and potential data loss.