Before the Transformer, sequence models like Recurrent Neural Networks processed information sequentially, creating
bottlenecks for long sequences and hindering parallelization. While Convolutional Networks offered some parallel
computation, they struggled with capturing long-range dependencies efficiently. The groundbreaking 'Attention Is All You
Need' paper introduced the Transformer, a novel architecture that entirely removed recurrence and convolutions. This
model aimed to boost training speed and handle distant relationships by relying solely on attention mechanisms.
At its core, attention is a mechanism that allows a model to weigh the importance of different parts of the input
sequence when processing each element. It functions by mapping a 'query' to a set of 'key-value' pairs. The query vector
interacts with all key vectors, determining a relevance score for each. These scores are then used to compute a weighted
sum of the value vectors, forming the output, allowing the model to focus on pertinent information.
The Transformer primarily uses Scaled Dot-Product Attention, where the dot products of queries and keys are scaled by
the square root of the key's dimension, before applying a softmax function. This scaling prevents large dot products
from leading to vanishing gradients. Multi-Head Attention extends this by running several attention mechanisms in
parallel on different linear projections of the input. This enables the model to jointly attend to information from
various representation subspaces and different positions, enhancing its ability to capture diverse dependencies.
The Transformer's Encoder block is responsible for processing the input sequence into a rich, contextual
representation. Each identical encoder layer consists of two main sub-layers: a Multi-Head Self-Attention mechanism,
which allows tokens to interact with all other tokens in the input sequence, and a Position-wise Feed-Forward Network.
Crucially, each sub-layer employs residual connections followed by layer normalization, aiding in gradient flow and
stabilizing training in deep networks.
The Decoder block generates the output sequence, one token at a time. It also features identical layers, but with three
sub-layers. The first is a Masked Multi-Head Self-Attention, which prevents the decoder from attending to future tokens
during training, mimicking inference. The second is an Encoder-Decoder Attention layer, where queries come from the
decoder's previous layer, and keys/values come from the encoder's output, enabling the decoder to focus on relevant
parts of the input. Finally, a Position-wise Feed-Forward Network processes the combined information before a final
softmax layer predicts the next token.
Since the Transformer processes all tokens in parallel without recurrence or convolutions, it inherently loses
information about the order of the sequence. To compensate, Positional Encodings are added to the input embeddings.
These encodings are generated using sine and cosine functions of varying frequencies, allowing the model to
differentiate between token positions and learn relative positional relationships. This simple yet ingenious addition
provides the necessary sequential context to the attention mechanisms.
The Transformer's architecture proved revolutionary, achieving state-of-the-art results on machine translation tasks,
significantly outperforming previous recurrent and convolutional models in terms of quality. Its reliance on attention
enabled unparalleled parallelization during training, drastically reducing computation time and allowing for larger
models. By efficiently capturing long-range dependencies, the Transformer laid the groundwork for countless
advancements, becoming the foundational architecture for nearly all modern large language models and a cornerstone of
contemporary AI research.