Imagine your API is suddenly hit with ten times its normal traffic. Without rate limiting, your servers would buckle
under the load, database connections would max out, and your entire service could go down. Rate limiting is the shield
that protects your system. It controls how many requests a client can make in a given time window — ensuring fair usage
and preventing both accidental overloads and malicious abuse. In this lesson, we'll explore the core algorithms behind
rate limiting, how to implement them at scale, and where to place them in your architecture.
The token bucket is the most widely used rate limiting algorithm, and understanding it is key to designing any rate
limiter. Here's how it works: tokens are added to a bucket at a fixed rate — say, ten tokens per second. The bucket has
a maximum capacity. When a request arrives, it must consume one token. If the bucket is empty, the request is rejected.
The beauty of this design is that it naturally allows bursts. If no requests have arrived for a while, tokens accumulate
up to the bucket capacity, allowing a short burst of traffic. This makes it ideal for APIs where occasional spikes are
expected.
While the token bucket allows bursts, the leaky bucket takes the opposite approach — and this distinction is critical
for choosing the right algorithm. Think of it as a bucket with a small hole at the bottom. Requests flow in at whatever
rate they arrive, but they drain out — that is, get processed — at a constant, fixed rate. If requests arrive faster
than the drain rate, the bucket fills up. Once full, excess requests simply overflow and are dropped. This guarantees a
perfectly smooth output rate, making it ideal for scenarios where downstream services need a steady, predictable flow of
traffic.
Both bucket algorithms work well, but fixed time windows have a subtle problem: a burst of requests at the boundary
between two windows can effectively double your intended limit. The sliding window counter solves this elegantly.
Instead of resetting counters at window boundaries, it uses a weighted combination of the current window's count and the
previous window's count. For example, if we're thirty percent into the current window, the effective count is seventy
percent of the previous window plus one hundred percent of the current one. This smooths out the boundary spike while
keeping memory usage low — just two counters instead of a full request log.
In production, you rarely have just one API server. When requests are spread across multiple servers, each needs to
check against the same rate limit — and that requires shared state. Redis is the go-to solution here. Using the atomic
INCR command paired with EXPIRE, you can implement a distributed counter in just two operations. For more precise
sliding windows, Lua scripts running inside Redis ensure atomicity. The challenge is handling race conditions and clock
differences across servers, but Redis's single-threaded execution model makes the counter operations inherently safe.
Now that we understand the algorithms, where exactly should we enforce rate limits? The most common choice is the API
Gateway — it's the single entry point for all traffic, making it easy to apply limits centrally before requests fan out
to microservices. For more granular control, you can add rate limiting as middleware within individual services. Some
systems use both: a gateway-level limit for overall protection and service-level limits for per-endpoint control.
Client-side rate limiting can help as a courtesy, but it should never be your only defense since it can be easily
bypassed.
When a request exceeds the rate limit, your system needs to respond clearly and helpfully. The standard response is
HTTP 429 Too Many Requests, which tells the client exactly what happened. Include a Retry-After header specifying how
many seconds the client should wait before trying again. Well-behaved clients will implement exponential backoff —
waiting longer after each rejection to avoid hammering the server. It's also important to distinguish between hard
limits, which reject immediately, and soft limits, which may queue or delay requests instead of dropping them.
Let's bring everything together. When designing a rate limiter, start by choosing your algorithm: use token bucket if
you need to allow bursts, leaky bucket for smooth constant-rate processing, or sliding window for precise time-based
limiting. For distributed systems, Redis gives you the shared state you need with atomic operations. Place your rate
limiter at the API gateway for simplicity, and add per-service limits for granularity. Always return clear HTTP 429
responses with Retry-After headers so clients know how to behave. With these pieces in place, your system is protected,
fair, and resilient.